Guide to the Royal Dixon Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Royal Dixon Papers
1914-1962
1920-1962
03/2015-007
Dixon, Royal, 1885-1962; Snowden, Chester, 1900-1984
2.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes writings by Royal Dixon as well as other authors close to Dixon, biographical material, materials related to his teaching and his leadership of organizational activity, correspondence, research notes from his writings, and newspaper clippings the author collected.
Biographical Information:
Royal Dixon was a well-regarded naturalist in the early twentieth century. He was born in Huntsville, Texas to Elijah and Francis Elizabeth Dixon. The date of his birth has been contested and ranges anywhere from 1880 to 1885. He began his academic career at Sam Houston State Teachers College then on to the Morgan Park Academy, Chicago. Later, he was a special student at Chicago University and Columbia University. He served as the N.Y. Curator for the Department of Botany, Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago (1905-1910) and as a columnist for the Houston Chronicle (1910-1927). He also began the Dixon School Creative Writing which were primarily classes taught in his home. He was the founder of the First Church for Animal Rights. Dixon was active in working to increase rights for immigrants in the United States and wrote several essays asking for increased rights for the immigrant community. He lived much of his adult life with his partner Chester Snowden, a well-regarded local artist. Snowden worked with Dixon frequently by contributing work for his writing. After a debilitating car accident, Snowden took over as Dixon’s power of attorney and handled all of Dixon’s affairs.
He published several works on the role of nature in society including The Human Side of Plants, The Human Side of Animals, The Human Side of Birds and The Human Side of Trees. Dixon also wrote several short stories.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Typescripts
Topical Term:
Creative writing; Education; Emigration and immigration; Naturalism; Naturalists; Sexual minorities -- Southern States
Accruals:
Second accession March 16, 2015; Third accession May 11, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Chester D. Snowden Papers, 1922-1982 in the Archives of American Art (http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/chester-d-snowden-papers-10557)
Scope and Contents
This collection includes writings by Royal Dixon as well as other authors close to Dixon, biographical material, materials related to his teaching and his leadership of organizational activity, correspondence, research notes from his writings, and newspaper clippings the author collected. The collection is arranged to the folder level preserving the original arrangement as much as possible.
Detailed List of Contents
- Writing
  - Full-length works
    - Bird Personalities - boxed unbound typescript, undated (Box 1, Item 1)
    - The Ape of Heaven - bound typescript, undated (Box 1, Item 2)
    - The Lost Angel - bound typescript, undated (Box 1, Item 3)
    - Earth Hunger, Part First - bound typescript, 1945 (Box 1, Item 4)
    - Earth Hunger, Part Second - bound typescript, undated (Box 1, Item 5)
    - Earth Hunger Illustrations by Chester Snowden, undated (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Short stories
    - “Cultural Renaissance of the New South”, “Nature’s Creatures Well Prepared for Battle”, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - “The White Hope of Raccoon Country”, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - “Miss Emily’s Hope”, “The Conductor’s Story”, “None Knows the Day”, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - “The Miracle”, “The Old Sherriff’s Story”, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - “Buber Licks His Pa before Breakfast”, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - “Were Adam and Eve Black?”, “The Swamp Woman”, “Miss Lucy’s Farm”, “The Old Pine Tree”, “Scandal at Shiloh Church”, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - “The Three Angelinas”, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Other writings
    - Syndicate and Fracture Articles; Houston Press, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - “Miracles of Science” - essays, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - “My Invisible Advisor” - typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Half Dark Moon - typescript and materials, 1939-1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Biographical and autobiographical materials
  - Chester Snowden’s notes on Royal Dixon, 1892-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Biographical correspondence, 1916-1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Biographical notes - Royal Dixon, 1893-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Biographical and autobiographical notes, 1936-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Biographical and autobiographical notes including Waxahachie car accident, 1924-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Biographical notes and correspondence, 1936-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Biographical notes and ephemera, 1919-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Royal Dixon’s notes on meditation and spiritual study, 1967-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Who’s Who in the West - Royal Dixon entry materials, 1880-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence regarding manuscripts - general, 1916-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence regarding The Ape of Heaven including legal documents, 1923-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Teaching and Leadership of Organization Materials
  - Ethical Cultural Group - clippings, notes, and minutes, 1933-1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lecture notes for writing class, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Student writing samples - graded, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Research Notes
  - Notes from lectures on herbs and plants, 1930-1934 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Research notes - Philology, 1914-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Writings by Other Authors
  - Writings by Chester Snowden
    - “Christmas in Tawnybleeton” - typescripts and clippings, 1966-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - “Christmas in Tawnybleeton” - final copy and correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - “Christmas in Tawnybleeton” - final copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - “Miss Emily’s Hope”, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - “The Hermitage”, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Poems, 1932-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Other writings
    - Poems written to Royal Dixon- various authors, 1919-1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper clippings - copies, 1931-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper clippings - original, 1931-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)